<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://danforth-restorative.com//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://danforth-restorative.com//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-01-19T20:14:59-05:00</updated><id>https://danforth-restorative.com//feed.xml</id><title type="html">Danforth Danforth</title><subtitle>Personal blog and restorative practice: Nonviolence, Anti-Racism, Anti-Sexism; Personal, Emotional and Spiritual Development.</subtitle><author><name>David Danforth</name></author><entry><title type="html">Danforth Restorative and DigitalSkills.Info</title><link href="https://danforth-restorative.com//2020/10/07/digitalskills-restorative.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Danforth Restorative and DigitalSkills.Info" /><published>2020-10-07T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-01-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://danforth-restorative.com//2020/10/07/digitalskills-restorative</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://danforth-restorative.com//2020/10/07/digitalskills-restorative.html">&lt;p&gt;This is my personal blog, but it is also a place to share knowledge related to personal growth and social change. This post describes that relationship, and its connection to &lt;a href=&quot;https://digitalskills.info&quot;&gt;digitalskills.info&lt;/a&gt; where I share information for developing our digital skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-personal-blog&quot;&gt;A Personal Blog&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One purpose of this blog is to provide a space to reflect upon my addictions recovery, and share resources I’ve found most valuable for rebuilding my life. This is a space where I will try to be vulnerable, and open up about some of my struggles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that my struggles do not exist in isolation, and I want to make this process transparent to any individuals or communities that I’ve impacted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I’ve learned during this process is that focusing too much on my problems can get in the way of solving them. It’s too easy to get lost in self-judgement and the pain of remembrance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve used that pain as a powerful incentive, devoting my energy to study, and the hard work of creating a life worth living. That is a continual practice, working towards positive for myself and others – a slow incremental progress that, little by little, has restored vibrancy to life – restructuring my thoughts, habits, hobbies and means of living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;danforth-restorative&quot;&gt;Danforth Restorative&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog is also a place to get beyond my personal struggle, and raise up in the rallying cry around social issues I’ve stayed willfully ignorant about for too long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to acknowledge the systemic problems of sexism and racism, and make the information surrounding them easier to navigate. This is for my own education, to make them more approachable for others, on the web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important to be aware of our personal and societal problems, but also to get practical and seek creative ways to solve them. For me, that involves helping to proliferate the best information I can find, and create content that makes this more relatable to others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;digitalskillsinfo&quot;&gt;DigitalSkills.Info&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;digital-skills-a-force-multiplier&quot;&gt;Digital Skills A Force Multiplier&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to my personal studies, I’ve spent these years in recovery immersed in the challenge of developing marketable digital skills. Especially in the beginning, this work has been a replacement addiction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drawing my focus on the multitude of challenges, technical and otherwise, of building a career online, I was able to find some relief from the initial agony of sobriety and facing my internal processes loud and clear, after years of dulling my senses in drink and drug.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That process has been very empowering, I got a taste for the impact one person can make on the web, simply making useful information more accessible. I’ve also gotten a taste for the powerful tools available on the web, and how they can multiply the impact that one person can make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;digital-skills-personal-growth-social-struggles-and-transformative-potential&quot;&gt;Digital skills, personal growth, social struggles, and transformative potential&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The focus of DigitalSkills.Info is to help make digital skills more accessible. On one hand, they are increasingly required to be employable. On the other hand, these skills can prove invaluable when used towards societal struggles.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>David Danforth</name></author><category term="Danforth Restorative" /><summary type="html">This is my personal blog, but it is also a place to share knowledge related to personal growth and social change. This post describes that relationship, and its connection to digitalskills.info where I share information for developing our digital skills.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Introduction to Nonviolent Communication</title><link href="https://danforth-restorative.com//2020/07/22/nonviolent-communication.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introduction to Nonviolent Communication" /><published>2020-07-22T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-07-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://danforth-restorative.com//2020/07/22/nonviolent-communication</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://danforth-restorative.com//2020/07/22/nonviolent-communication.html">&lt;p&gt;Nonviolent communication is a value system designed to promote peace on the planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It includes a philosophy and communication framework that lead to compassionate giving and meeting the needs of all participants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first encountered this message in a youtube video from an April 2000 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=l7TONauJGfc&quot;&gt;introductory workshop hosted by Marshall Rosenberg&lt;/a&gt;. Marshall shares stories of using this technique for negotiation in longstanding tribal conflicts, racial violence, marital disputes, and healing mental\emotional wounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s underlying philosophy provides clarity around how we think about our emotions and fundamental human needs, and lays the groundwork for empathic connection with the people in our lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- excerpt --&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/l7TONauJGfc&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marshall_Rosenberg&quot;&gt;Marshall Rosenberg&lt;/a&gt; developed this system after having grown up experiencing, both, extreme violence and compassion under difficult conditions. He went on to study psychology with the intention to discover what conditions contribute to violence on the planet and what helps us connect us with our compassionate nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earning a Ph.D. in clinical psychology from the University of Wisconsin–Madison, Dr. Rosenberg found that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2019/07/190708131152.htm&quot;&gt;psychiatric diagnoses have no scientific basis&lt;/a&gt;, and that looking at violence as a mental illness ignored the societal structures that promote this behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He found that religions of the world agree we’re meant to live compassionately, but don’t necessarily explain how to do that. He then studied the differences between the people, he knew, who were the most compassionate, and those who seemed to enjoy criticizing, blaming, and attacking others. He used this research along with his education in psychology to develop this process of called nonviolent communication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While developing NVC, he found the process to be much more effective as a healing tool, in his practice of clinical psychology, than how he was taught to do psychotherapy in university.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;premise&quot;&gt;Premise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonviolent communication requires a radical transformation of our habits in communication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Rosenberg suggests that people have been &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.opendemocracy.net/en/transformation/transforming-powers-continuing-relevance-of-walter-wink/&quot;&gt;living under domination structures&lt;/a&gt; for most of recorded history, where some people claim to be superior, having the right to control others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People living under those structures have been taught a system of retributive justice, where if you are judged as good by authorities then you deserve to be rewarded, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www2.goshen.edu/~joannab/women/wink99.pdf&quot;&gt;if you are judged as bad by the authorities, you deserve to suffer&lt;/a&gt;. Additionally, we’ve learned to use a type of &lt;em&gt;language that describes what people are&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;strong&gt;good&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;bad&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;right&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;wrong&lt;/strong&gt;; rather than how their actions impact our lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Rosenberg taught that whenever we’re feeling anger, depression, guilt, or shame, we’re thinking in a way that contributes to violence, a way of thinking designed to make us obedient to authority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OJ Harvey took samples of literature from around the world to discover how often language was used judging people’s actions in this way, and then correlated that with measures of violence towards oneself and others, finding a high &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/stream/conceptualsystem00harv/conceptualsystem00harv_djvu.txt&quot;&gt;correlation between the language of moralistic judgement and violence&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast, Nonviolent communication focuses our attention on whether actions peoples actions are fulfilling our needs or not. Our own actions, and the actions of others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of judging what people are, we make clear observations of whether their actions are fulfilling our needs. If our needs are not met, then we follow up our observation with a clear request of what would meet those needs. If our needs are met by their actions, we clearly communicate an appreciation of how our lives have been enriched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;components&quot;&gt;Components&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The language of nonviolent communication consists of &lt;strong&gt;Feelings&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Needs&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Observations&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Requests&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;feelings&quot;&gt;Feelings&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process of nonviolent communication begins with our feelings, and requires that we learn to identify and name our emotions. To help with that there are some lists of different type of feeling words.  To say ‘I feel good’, or ‘I feel bad’, isn’t very descriptive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we do feel good, there are likely a number of other words that would more adequately convey what’s alive in us. Just as when we aren’t feeling well, there are more descriptive words that can more accurately convey our emotional state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;our-feelings-when-needs-are-met&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nycnvc.org/feelings/&quot;&gt;Our Feelings When Needs are Met&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AFFECTIONATE&lt;/strong&gt;: compassionate, fond, loving, 
tender, warm&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ENGAGED&lt;/strong&gt;: absorbed, curious, engrossed, enthralled, entranced, fascinated, interested, intrigued, involved, open, spellbound, stimulated&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EXCITED&lt;/strong&gt;: amazed, ardent, aroused, energetic, enlivened, enthusiastic, exuberant, invigorated, lively, passionate, surprised, vibrant&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EXHILARATED&lt;/strong&gt;: enthralled, radiant, electrified, overjoyed, thrilled&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GRATEFUL&lt;/strong&gt;: appreciative, moved, thankful, touched&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HAPPY&lt;/strong&gt;: amused, blissful, cheerful, ecstatic, elated, giddy, glad, jolly, joyful, jubilant, merry, overjoyed, pleased, rapturous, tickled&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HOPEFUL&lt;/strong&gt;: confident, expectant, jazzed, sanguine, up, upbeat&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;INSPIRED&lt;/strong&gt;: amazed, eager, enthused, moved, psyched, stimulated, stirred, wonder&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PEACEFUL&lt;/strong&gt;: calm, comfortable, centered, equanimity, fulfilled, mellow, open, quiet, relaxed, relieved, satisfied, serene, tranquil&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;REFRESHED&lt;/strong&gt;: recharged, rejuvenated, renewed, restored, revived&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;feelings-associated-with-unmet-needs&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nycnvc.org/feelings/&quot;&gt;Feelings Associated with Unmet Needs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ANGER&lt;/strong&gt;: aggravated, angry, animosity, annoyed, contempt, disgruntled, enraged, furious, hate , hostile, incensed, irate, irritated, irked, livid, nettled, outraged, peeved, resentful&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AVERSION&lt;/strong&gt;: abhorrence, appalled, bothered displeased, disgust, dislike, enmity, horrified, loathing, repulsion, revulsion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CONFUSION&lt;/strong&gt;: ambivalent, baffled bewildered, conflicted, dazed, discombobulated, disoriented, mixed, mystified, perplexed, puzzled, torn&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DISCONNECTION&lt;/strong&gt;: apathetic, bored, closed, 
detached, distant, indifferent, listless, numb, withdrawn&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DISQUIET&lt;/strong&gt;: agitated, alarmed, concerned, distraught, disconcerted, dismayed, disturbed, frustrated, perturbed, rattled, restless, shocked, startled, surprised, troubled, turbulent, turmoil, uncomfortable, uneasy, unnerved, unsettled, upset&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EMBARRASSMENT&lt;/strong&gt;: ashamed, chagrined, discomfited, flustered, mortified, self-conscious&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FATIGUE&lt;/strong&gt;: beat, burnt out, depleted, exhausted, listless, pooped, sleepy, tired, weary, wiped out, worn out&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FEAR&lt;/strong&gt;: afraid, anxious, apprehensive, dread, fearful, foreboding, frightened, guarded,  insecure, leery, mistrustful, panicked, petrified, scared, shaky, terrified,  trepidation, wary, worried&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PAIN&lt;/strong&gt;: aching, agony, anguished, devastated, grief, heartbroken, hungry, hurting, lonely, miserable, regretful, remorseful&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SADNESS&lt;/strong&gt;: depressed, dejected, despairing, despondent, disappointed, discouraged, disheartened, forlorn, gloomy, heavy hearted,  hopeless, melancholy, miserable, unhappy, wistful&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TENSION&lt;/strong&gt;: anxious, closed, distressed, 
edgy, fidgety, frazzled, frustrated, jittery,nervous, overwhelmed, restless, stressed out&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;YEARNING&lt;/strong&gt;: longing, nostalgic, pining&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“People are disturbed not by things, but by the view they take of them.” —Epictetus&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important premise underlying nonviolent communication is that it’s our thinking that causes our emotions, not external events. Other people’s words or behavior may very well be the stimulus for our feelings, but they are never the cause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;needs&quot;&gt;Needs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In nonviolent communication, part of understanding our feelings is identifying which needs of ours are related to those feelings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Rosenberg developed a list of what he determined to be &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nycnvc.org/feelings/&quot;&gt;funadmental human needs&lt;/a&gt;, based on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.daghammarskjold.se/wp-content/uploads/1989/05/89_1.pdf&quot;&gt;the work of Max-Neef&lt;/a&gt;, a Chilean economist who determined that the best way to measure an economy based on whether it’s meeting the needs of its people or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;needs-inventory&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnvc.org/training/resource/needs-inventory&quot;&gt;Needs Inventory&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;(c) 2005 by Center for Nonviolent Communication&lt;br /&gt;
Website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnvc.org&quot;&gt;www.cnvc.org&lt;/a&gt; Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:cnvc@cnvc.org&quot;&gt;cnvc@cnvc.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Phone: +1.505-244-4041&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CONNECTION&lt;/strong&gt;: acceptance, affection, appreciation, belonging, cooperation, communication, closeness, community, companionship, compassion, consideration, consistency, empathy, inclusion, intimacy, love, mutuality, nurturing, respect/self-respect, safety, security, stability, support, to know and be known, to see and be seen, to understand and be understood, trust, warmth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PHYSICAL WELL-BEING&lt;/strong&gt;: air, food, movement/exercise, rest/sleep, sexual expression, safety, shelter, touch, water&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HONESTY&lt;/strong&gt;: authenticity, integrity, presence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PLAY&lt;/strong&gt;: joy, humor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PEACE&lt;/strong&gt;: beauty, communion, ease, equality, harmony, inspiration, order&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AUTONOMY&lt;/strong&gt;: choice, freedom, independence, space, spontaneity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MEANING&lt;/strong&gt;: awareness, celebration of life, challenge, clarity, competence, consciousness, contribution, creativity, discovery, efficacy, effectiveness, growth, hope, learning, mourning, participation, purpose, self-expression, stimulation, to matter, understanding&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;needs-vs-strategies&quot;&gt;Needs vs Strategies&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A premise of NVC is that all actions are attempts to meet human needs, and that our conflicts are never at the level of those needs, but in the strategies we employ attempting to meet those needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking for the un-met need helps us to transcend the strategy level, where we can easily get caught in conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;observations&quot;&gt;Observations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The ability to observe without evaluating is the highest form of intelligence.” - Jiddu Krishnamurti&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Begin with a clear observation of what behavior has stimulating our emotions, avoiding language that sounds like criticism or blame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This part might sound simple, but we’re accustomed to making evaluations of what type of person they are, because of their actions, rather than how those actions affected our needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Observations are contrasted with diagnoses. An observation connected with a need might sound like, “I have a need for tranquility when its time for bed, and when you didn’t come home on time angry and afraid”. The diagnosis could sound like “you don’t care about me, you only ever think of yourself”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of those statements could be a response to the same situation, but in nonviolent communication we avoid diagnosing what we think people are. We create clear observations of a behavior and which needs of ours were, or were not, met by that behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;requests&quot;&gt;Requests&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If our needs are not met in a situation, it’s important to be clear what would meet our needs in this moment, avoiding vague language, or only stating what you don’t want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We might like for others to anticipate our needs before we even are aware of them, but often we’re not very clear ourselves about exactly what will meet our needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;requests-vs-demands&quot;&gt;Requests vs Demands&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Avoid presenting requests in a way that sound like a demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever we get people to do things from fear of punishment, shame or guilt, we are experienced as a source of violence, who will make the suffer if they don’t comply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To illustrate the danger of a language that denies choice, Rosenberg provides the example of Nazi war criminal Adolph Eichmann.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At his war trial, asked if it was difficult to send thousands to their deaths, Eichmann responded that their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Sk9-3bMAGBw&quot;&gt;bureaucratic language&lt;/a&gt; made it easy. If someone asked why they did it, they would say ‘I had no choice’, ‘superiors orders’, ‘it’s the law’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of this concern, nonviolent communication emphasizes that we avoid any language that implies we have no choice, and suggests that the use of words like ‘have to’, ‘ought’, ‘must’ results in people who don’t feel responsible for their actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonviolent communication has a handful of moving parts, and involves learning a new way to think about ourselves and our relationships. While it’s not an overly complex system, it does express some profound truths that I’m not sure I’m able to properly convey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most impactful, to me, is the concept of retributive justice. I’ve begun to see how deeply ingrained it is, in my own consciousness, and the world around me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel like there’s a lot of ground for me to cover still, in nonviolent communication. I intend to spend a lot more time working on this, what I believe to be the most valuable teaching available for promoting peace on the plant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;further-study&quot;&gt;Further Study&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some links where you can find more information in Articles, Books, Video, Podcasts, and Research Studies&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnvc.org/&quot;&gt;Center for Nonviolent Communication&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnvc.org/training/resource/book-chapter-1&quot;&gt;Nonviolent Communication: A Language of Life&lt;/a&gt; - Chapter 1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nonviolentcommunication.com/learn-nonviolent-communication/&quot;&gt;PuddleDancer Press&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://puddledancer.bookstore.ipgbook.com/&quot;&gt;NVC Bookstore&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nonviolentcommunication.com/learn-nonviolent-communication/research-on-nvc/&quot;&gt;Research&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=l7TONauJGfc&quot;&gt;The Basics of Nonviolent Communication, with Marshall B. Rosenberg, PhD&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLPNVcESwoWu4lI9C3bhkYIWB8-dphbzJ3&quot;&gt;NVC Training Sessions 1-9 Marshall Rosenberg Nonviolent Communication&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://workcollaboratively.com/podcast/&quot;&gt;Connecting Across Differences&lt;/a&gt; - a podcast by Dian Killian, Ph.D. of Work Collaboratively about having greater empathy for yourself and others, and how to hear others more deeply and make sure that you’ve been heard.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.artofnvc.com/podcast-1&quot;&gt;The Art of NVC&lt;/a&gt; - Podcast dedicated to sharing, learning, and discovering the fundamentals of Nonviolent Communication based on what I have learned from Marshall Rosenberg’s classic book “Nonviolent Communication” and many of his videos.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>David Danforth</name></author><category term="Nonviolence" /><summary type="html">Instead of judging what people are, we make clear observations of whether their actions are fulfilling our needs. If our needs are not met, then we follow up our observation with a clear request of what would meet those needs. If our needs are met by their actions, we clearly communicate an appreciation of how our lives have been enriched.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://danforth-restorative.com//assets/images/Nonviolent-Communication_Language-of-Life.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://danforth-restorative.com//assets/images/Nonviolent-Communication_Language-of-Life.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Opening up after a few years of isolation, since I stopped drinking</title><link href="https://danforth-restorative.com//2020/07/20/introduction.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Opening up after a few years of isolation, since I stopped drinking" /><published>2020-07-20T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-07-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://danforth-restorative.com//2020/07/20/introduction</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://danforth-restorative.com//2020/07/20/introduction.html">&lt;p&gt;I quit drinking and drugs almost three years ago, although I’ve only been approaching something resembling sobriety since the beginning of this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I quit drinking, I’d been on a downward spiral for quite some time. My behavior and mindset deteriorated to a shameful state. I was stuck in a cycle of addiction that I didn’t know how to escape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I drank, I didn’t have to be concerned with anything of import, I’d regulate my emotions with a 6 pack. I knew I had to find a different way, but that was easier said than done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gratefully, I had some help coming to the stark realization of exactly how far I’d fallen, and a family who cares to support the long road of recovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- excerpt --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/david.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I grew up with a lot of pain that I attributed to the world around me. While I had some just grievances, much of my angst was misguided. It’s taken far too too long, for me to realize that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead I bitterly rejected what I saw as adversarial social convention meant to control. I inherently distrusted all social structures, which was a direct impediment to becoming a part of anything larger than myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I set out, in 2007, as a seeker of truth. I had the idea that the world was broken. That corruption and lies were embedded into every sphere of life, that the system was set up against the many for the benefit of the few. While that may be true, my reaction to those perceived injustices increased my own suffering and that of others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I shed the external trappings of domination, I sought fulfillment in drugs, alcohol, sex, self-serving pursuits and fleeting experiences. I was full of bitterness, on a self-indulgent trip simply trying to escape, doing nothing to improve my situation or the world around me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the intervening years, plenty of others have worked tirelessly, to make the world a better place, and improved many of the issues I care about.. while I was falling behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a lot of remorse, and have suffered a great deal of anguish, about some of my actions, and state of being, over the years I spent on the road. I was judgemental, self-righteous, had an unhealthy attitude towards women, made increasingly poor decisions, and grew to cherish my addictions over reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m here to try and speak to all of that, make clear where my current state of mind and intentions are at, and begin working to improve situations that I’ve negatively impacted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nonviolent-communication&quot;&gt;Nonviolent Communication&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A major turning point in my recovery has been finding &lt;a href=&quot;https://baynvc.org/basics-of-nonviolent-communication/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nonviolent Communication&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (NVC). I started listening to workshops given by Marshall Rosenberg, at the recommendation of my counselor. NVC is now the cornerstone to my recovery, easily the most valuable teaching I’ve ever encountered, and the main reason I’m here and able to write this message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d heard about Nonviolent Communication years ago, once upon a time I thought I knew generally what it was, and even practiced it to a limited extent. I can see now that I had no inkling of its depth or potency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Nonviolent communication (NVC) consists of a value system that challenges ways of thinking that create violence on this planet. 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnvc.org/training/resource/book-chapter-1&quot;&gt;Nonviolent Communication: A Language of Life&lt;/a&gt; - Marshall Rosenberg&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of nonviolent communication is to communicate in such a way where the needs of all participants are met, so that co-operation is come to willingly, never out of guilt, shame, or from trying to buy approval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even being new to the subject, learning about the process and it’s underlying philosophy, my relationship with family rapidly improved, and I was able to move past a great deal of anger, by recognizing where it’s misplaced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The message of Nonviolent Communication has helped to begin repairing old wounds, and show me a path towards life enriching human relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;trying-to-find-a-path-forward&quot;&gt;Trying to find a path forward&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important for me to not only find healing, but make whatever positive impact in the lives of others that I’m able, and perhaps repair some of the damage I perpetuated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past year, I’ve delved into Cognitive Behavioral Therapy (CBT), emotional literacy, mindfulness, restorative practices, the mechanics behind addiction, and important messages that are gaining traction lately, including that Black Lives Matter and the #metoo movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not able to devote all of my time to these pursuits, but my energy has been shifting in that direction, since around the new year. I have been saving up a lot of bookmarks, so I’d like to begin sharing regularly on &lt;em&gt;all of the above&lt;/em&gt; and see where that goes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>David Danforth</name></author><category term="Danforth Restorative" /><summary type="html">I quit drinking and drugs almost three years ago, although I've only been approaching something resembling sobriety since the beginning of this year.</summary></entry></feed>