<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://danforth-restorative.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://danforth-restorative.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-03-02T00:47:44-05:00</updated><id>https://danforth-restorative.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">David Danforth</title><subtitle>Personal Blog and Restorative Practice: Nonviolence, Anti-Racism, Anti-Sexism; Personal Growth, Emotional and Spiritual Development.</subtitle><author><name>David Danforth</name></author><entry><title type="html">Helping things go right &amp;gt; Dealing with things going wrong</title><link href="https://danforth-restorative.com/2021/02/26/helping-things-go-right.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Helping things go right &amp;gt; Dealing with things going wrong" /><published>2021-02-26T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-02-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://danforth-restorative.com/2021/02/26/helping-things-go-right</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://danforth-restorative.com/2021/02/26/helping-things-go-right.html">&lt;p&gt;When I first quit drinking after nearly a decade of daily consumption of alcohol and other substances, my emotions, previously regulated with a steady intake of alcohol, turned up to a piercing amplitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent a lot of time thinking about what was wrong with me, digging to the roots of my failings, I was full of shame and blame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t understand this during my years as a drop-out, but I can see now that nihilism is among the roots of my addiction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I structured my life to avoid the strictures of society. I decided that the system was corrupted beyond repair and my only bet was to escape it. But &lt;em&gt;I didn’t take too much thought to the type of life I wanted to create&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I did largely escape the fetters of societal convention, I openly embraced the trap of intoxicants, a continual process of acquiring booze and fantastical experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I utterly failed to recognize the varied benefits of social convention, until I drifted far too far from its shores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the beginning of my recovery, I spent a lot of time thinking about these type of things. Its an essential component to the recovery process, confronting oneself and taking account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A friend told me about therapy – if doesn’t hurt, you’re not doing it right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the same, pouring all of my energy towards critical self-examination can be counter-productive, after a point. Over time, I’ve found it more productive to put energy towards becoming the person I want to be, than to overly dwell on my failings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more time I spend developing myself, the better I am able to process difficult reflections on regretful actions over a decade of embracing my addictions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Change Pyramid&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/change-pyramid.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arbinger.com/Landing/AnatomyOfPeace.html&quot;&gt;The Anatomy of Peace&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m getting the sense that sometimes focusing on a problem can make it more difficult to solve. This goes along with the idea that we are created by our thoughts, or that we become as we think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focusing on positive and productive directions for my energy creates the inner good-will necessary to face my biggest challenges and failings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also considering broader societal problems in a similar fashion. I want to address them more directly, in the future. For now I’m focused on learnings that strengthen under-developed areas of culture that help contribute to our problems, before confronting them directly on this blog and otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While racism and sexism are problems that broadly impact society and culture, I must first challenge and transform their expression within myself. I’m still at the beginning of that process, and frustratingly, I often note those expressions in my thoughts and reactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I grew up in an age where women were not considered as intelligent or capable as men. I’m ashamed to say that regardless of what I believe, that idea still impacts my reactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also have grown up exposed to casual racism. Even though I never embraced that racism consciously, it also has been imprinted upon my brain and my judgement, one way or the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Confronting the sexism and racism in myself is relatively simple. Confronting their systemic manifestations is a greater challenge. As possible I will relate any insights that arise while confronting them in myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thanks-for-reading&quot;&gt;Thanks for reading&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote this post, in part, because I noticed that some of my proposed topics for this blog aren’t directly the subject of its contents. Instead, its content is meant to address the underlying issues, according to my recovery plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea I’m exploring is that solving a problem doesn’t always look like confronting it directly. Often, what we think of as a problem is actually symptom of underlying issues, rather than the actual cause.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>David Danforth</name></author><category term="Nonviolence" /><summary type="html">I noticed that some of my proposed topics for this blog aren't directly the subject of its contents. That has something to do with the idea that some of the most important work in my recovery hasn't been trying to solve the problems I'd caused for myself. Exploring the idea that solving a problem often doesn't always look like confronting it directly. What we think of as a problem may be closer to a symptom of underlying issues.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://danforth-restorative.com/assets/images/the-change-pyramid.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://danforth-restorative.com/assets/images/the-change-pyramid.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Rise of Nonviolence: Gandhi, King, Wink, Rosenberg</title><link href="https://danforth-restorative.com/2021/01/21/rise-of-nonviolence-gandhi-king-wink-rosenberg.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Rise of Nonviolence: Gandhi, King, Wink, Rosenberg" /><published>2021-01-21T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-01-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://danforth-restorative.com/2021/01/21/rise-of-nonviolence%E2%80%93gandhi-king-wink-rosenberg</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://danforth-restorative.com/2021/01/21/rise-of-nonviolence-gandhi-king-wink-rosenberg.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gandhi-king-wink-rosenberg.webp&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mahatmas Gandhi was the first in modern times to take Jesus’ message of nonviolence seriously. Fueled by love, he galvanized a mass movement that helped to free India from British rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inspired by the example of Gandhi’s nonviolent resistance, and also by the message of nonviolent Jesus, Martin Luther King Jr led the US civil rights movement that fought for equal treatment under the law for African Americans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gandhi and King offer powerful examples of what is possible with a commitment to nonviolent resistance, fueled by love. Their nonviolent practices have been followed to great effect, but their examples of love, in the face of oppression are harder to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That could have something to do with that theologian Walter Wink called the Myth of Redemptive Violence, that’s been repeated in nearly every story ever told.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, Marshall Rosenberg found the root of violence in the way we speak and think. He also taught a language way of thinking to transform it into a way of thinking and speaking that serve life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;nonviolent-impact&quot;&gt;Nonviolent Impact&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article follows the philosophy and practice of nonviolence, as taught and lived by some of its greatest leaders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But first, lets step back and review what exactly is nonviolence, along with its impact and proliferation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonviolence is not pacifism, nor does it mean simply abstaining from violence. Nonviolence is a creative pursuit which seeks peaceful means to resist oppression, resolve conflicts, and bring about change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.journalofdemocracy.org/articles/the-future-of-nonviolent-resistance-2/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/nonviolent-vs-violent.webp&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you haven’t already been immersed in the culture and media of nonviolence, it may surprise you to learn that nonviolent resistance is more popular than ever, while also being more effective than violent strategies.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As long as we are reliant on corporate media for news about the world, we’re unlikely to learn about the rise of nonviolence or its growing impact on our planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.journalofdemocracy.org/articles/the-future-of-nonviolent-resistance-2/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/nonviolent-vs-violent-success-rates.webp&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One reason for that is that humans have evolved so that &lt;a href=&quot;https://letter.ly/negative-news-statistics/&quot;&gt;negative stories and experiences captivate us more deeply&lt;/a&gt; than positive stories and experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another reason is that the corporate media has a lot more funding and is highly organized in a centralized fashion, where nonviolence is a grass-roots affair that is only beginning to achieve a measure of global co-ordination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;opposition-vs-proliferation-of-nonviolence&quot;&gt;Opposition vs Proliferation of Nonviolence&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://1lib.us/book/1309893/256eca&quot;&gt;Nonviolence: the history of a dangerous idea&lt;/a&gt;, Mark Kurlansky tells the story of proponents of nonviolence, throughout the ages, and the opposition they have faced from the state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the ages, champions of nonviolence have been persecuted and crucified, their message co-opted and modified, its intent suppressed, to enable violence enforced by the state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nonviolence:_The_History_of_a_Dangerous_Idea&quot;&gt;25 Lessons of Nonviolence&lt;/a&gt; (from Kurlansky’s book):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Practitioners of nonviolence are seen as enemies of the state.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Once a state takes over a religion, the religion loses its nonviolent teachings.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A rebel can be defanged and co-opted by making him a saint after he is dead.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Somewhere behind every war there are always a few founding lies.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all of the opposition that these ideas and their adherents have faced, the heart of nonviolence persists more widely-known and practiced than ever before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, activists have an arsenal of nonviolent techniques, tried and tested, at our disposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Albert Einstein Institution has classified &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brandeis.edu/peace-conflict/pdfs/198-methods-non-violent-action.pdf&quot;&gt;198 METHODS OF NONVIOLENT ACTION&lt;/a&gt; into three broad categories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;protest and persuasion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;noncooperation&lt;/strong&gt; (social, economic, and political)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;nonviolent intervention&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A description and historical examples of each can be found in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aeinstein.org/books/the-politics-of-nonviolent-action-part-2/&quot;&gt;Volume Two of The Politics of Nonviolent Action, by Gene Sharp&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aeinstein.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Preview-Politics-Part-II.pdf&quot;&gt;preview&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;nonviolent-roots&quot;&gt;Nonviolent Roots&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I’d like to set the backdrop by exploring the two most widely successful and well-known leaders of nonviolent resistance. Its important to consider what made these men great, what is their philosophy, and what is the structure of their practice?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mahatma-gandhi-1869--1948&quot;&gt;Mahatma Gandhi (1869 – 1948)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/mahatma-gandhi-310552_Clker-Free-Vector-Images.webp&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teachers of nonviolent practices and philosophy stretch back through recorded history. However, Gandhi was the first leader to take that message to the global stage. He brought together the principles of nonviolence into a coherent teaching and practice that have been used effectively to combat injustices and win political causes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spiritual component was central to the message of Gandhi. He preached a message of love, self sacrifice, and willingness to suffer for a cause. He was a devout soul who had a way of attracting national attention to his causes, bringing pressure to authorities, affecting positive change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are &lt;strong&gt;three central components to Gandhian nonviolence&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Ahimsa&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;satyagraha&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;tapasya&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ahimsa&quot;&gt;Ahimsa&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Literally speaking, &lt;strong&gt;Ahimsa&lt;/strong&gt; is a Sanskrit term meaning ‘non-injury’ or ‘non-killing’. Gandhi developed the term more fully to mean non-violence in thought, word, or deed towards all sentient beings. The term also implies strength of will, which Gandhi believed to be the seat of our power, rather than physical force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ahimsa, like nonviolence, is a general term under which a variety of practices could be categorized.  Truth and Love are at the core of Ahimsa, which is not related to pacifism, or a simple failure to harm, but an active process of doing good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;satyagraha&quot;&gt;Satyagraha&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Satyagraha&lt;/strong&gt;, on the other hand, involves practical use of nonviolent techniques for resisting unjust laws. It fulfills of ahimsa in the political realm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Satyagraha&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Satyagraha&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a compound word made of the words &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Satya&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;satya&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;em&gt;agraha&lt;/em&gt;. Satya means truth or essence, it root &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sat_(Sanskrit)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;sat&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; stands for &lt;em&gt;being&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;the true essence&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wisdomlib.org/definition/agraha#sanskrit&quot;&gt;Agraha&lt;/a&gt; means willpower, determination or persistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, satyagraha involves living aligned with ones true essence with great determination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Passive resistance does not necessarily avoid violence on principle, or love, but of necessity. Satyagraha is a force of love. Its greatest intent is not to defeat an opponent, but to win them over and convert them with heart, patience and steadfastness of purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Satyagraha, in fullness, does not involve winning at all costs, but is devoted first, to the truest or highest principle of being (&lt;em&gt;sat&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;tapasya&quot;&gt;Tapasya&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The greatest weapon of Gandhian nonviolence is &lt;strong&gt;Tapasya&lt;/strong&gt;, or voluntary suffering. Gandhi was a man of great determination and willingness to suffer for what is right. He believed that suffering for a cause to be more effective at converting others to his cause than discussion alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adherents of satyagraha suffer wrong with love in their heart, with the intention of winning over the wrongdoer. The satyagrahi does not equate the person with the harm that they bring about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a devoted practitioner finds a situation of harm they are willing to suffer for and can arouse a significant number of those subjected to the cause, much good can be done to bring about change in the matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These people take a pledge and begin a program of self-purification. This helps to strengthen their resolve, and ensure this path is undertaken from a moral high-ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;techniques&quot;&gt;Techniques&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fasting&lt;/strong&gt; - Fasting is a means for self-purification in preparation for a nonviolent campaign. Fasting is a spiritual tool and can also make a potent statement for your cause. A number of times Gandhi undertook a “fast unto death”, for serious grievances, successfully effecting reversal of injustices.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Peaceful Picketing&lt;/strong&gt; - Rallying people to promote their message in public to generate a consciousness of the issue at hand.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Civil Disobedience&lt;/strong&gt; - Peacefully disobeying unjust laws. Requires a general respect for the law, while disobeying a specific unjust law.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Non-cooperation&lt;/strong&gt; - While the government may perpetrate injustice, it also requires the participation of the people. Non-cooperation involves the people systematically withdrawing from participation with all aspects of unjust systems.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Constructive Program&lt;/strong&gt; - It’s important not only to protest and call for reform of practices we want abolished, but to establish a program for the overall betterment of our communities and society at large. The better and more positive structures we construct, the less need for civil resistance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;martin-luther-king-jr-1929---1968&quot;&gt;Martin Luther King Jr (1929 - 1968)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/martin-luther-king-OpenClipart-Vectors.webp&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The whole Gandhian concept of satyagraha (&lt;em&gt;satya&lt;/em&gt; is truth which equals love, and &lt;em&gt;graha&lt;/em&gt; is force; &lt;em&gt;satyagraha&lt;/em&gt; thus means truth-force or love-force) was profoundly significant to me. As I delved deeper into the philosophy of Gandhi my skepticism concerning the power of love gradually diminished, and I came to see for the first time that the Christian doctrine of love operating through the Gandhian method of nonviolence was one of the most potent weapons available to oppressed people in their struggle for freedom. - &lt;a href=&quot;https://kinginstitute.stanford.edu/king-papers/documents/pilgrimage-nonviolence&quot;&gt;Martin Luther King Jr.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. King’s earliest encounter with nonviolent resistance was reading Henry David Thoreau’s Civil Disobedience, while at Morehouse. During his studies in theological seminary he became influenced by the social gospel, reading &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.americanyawp.com/reader/20-the-progressive-era/walter-rauschenbusch-christianity-and-the-social-crisis-1907/&quot;&gt;Christianity and the Social Crisis&lt;/a&gt; by Walter Rauschenbusch. He then began a serious study of the social and ethical theories of the great philosophers. King had become quite skeptical of the power of love in resolving social struggles, that was until he encountered the teachings of Mahatma Gandhi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Little did he know that he would soon play an active role in nonviolent resistance. After graduating seminary, King became a pastor in Montgomery Alabama, where he was appointed spokesperson for the protesters who organized the Montgomery bus boycotts. During this time, his mind was drawn back to Jesus’ Sermon on the Mount and Gandhi’s methods of nonviolent resistance, seeing how Jesus provided the spirit and Gandhi provided the methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few years later, &lt;a href=&quot;https://kinginstitute.stanford.edu/encyclopedia/india-trip&quot;&gt;he would travel to India&lt;/a&gt;, to deepen his understanding of Gandhian Nonviolence and see its impact first-hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Since being in India, I am more convinced than ever before that the method of nonviolent resistance is the most potent weapon available to oppressed people in their struggle for justice and human dignity. In a real sense, Mahatma Gandhi embodied in his life certain universal principles that are inherent in the moral structure of the universe, and these principles are as inescapable as the law of gravitation”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;three-major-evils&quot;&gt;Three Major Evils&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr King spoke of 3 types of violence that he worked against, calling them the &lt;strong&gt;Three Major Evils&lt;/strong&gt;. Those evils are &lt;em&gt;racism&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;poverty&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;militarism&lt;/em&gt;. He saw them as inter-related, if we are to combat one of them, then we must combat them all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to work against these evils, it’s required to develop a nonviolent state of being. King outlined 6 principles to serve as a foundation for his teaching of nonviolent conflict resolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;6-principles-of-nonviolence&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://rcnv.org/resources/principles-nonviolence-martin-luther-king-jr/&quot;&gt;6 Principles of Nonviolence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PRINCIPLE 1: Nonviolence is a way of life for courageous people.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PRINCIPLE 2: Nonviolence seeks to win friendship and understanding, for the creation of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gse.harvard.edu/news/19/01/achieving-kings-beloved-community&quot;&gt;beloved community&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PRINCIPLE 3: Attack forces of evil not persons doing evil.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PRINCIPLE 4: Accept suffering without retaliation for the sake of the cause to achieve a goal.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PRINCIPLE 5: Avoid internal violence of the spirit as well as external physical violence.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PRINCIPLE 6: The universe is on the side of justice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;6-steps-of-nonviolent-social-change&quot;&gt;6 Steps of Nonviolent Social Change&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These principles have much in common with Gandhian values. They are meant to arouse our will to good and guide our efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Information gathering&lt;/strong&gt;: To understand and articulate an issue, problem or injustice facing a person, community, or institution, you must do research. You must investigate and gather all vital information from all sides of the argument or issue to increase your understanding of the problem. You must become an expert on your opponent’s position.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Education&lt;/strong&gt;: It is essential to inform others, including your opposition, about your issue. This minimises misunderstandings and gains your support and sympathy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Personal commitment&lt;/strong&gt;: Daily check and affirm your faith in the philosophy and methods of nonviolence. Eliminate hidden motives and prepare yourself to accept suffering, if necessary, in your work for justice.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Discussion/negotiation&lt;/strong&gt;: Using grace, humour and intelligence, confront the other party with a list of injustices and a plan for addressing and resolving these injustices. Look for what is positive in every action and statement the opposition makes. Do not seek to humiliate the opponent but to call forth the good in the opponent.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Direct action&lt;/strong&gt;: These are actions taken when the opponent is unwilling to enter into, or remain in, discussion/negotiation. These actions impose a “creative tension” into the conflict, supplying moral pressure on your opponent to work with you in resolving the injustice.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reconciliation&lt;/strong&gt;: Nonviolence seeks friendship and understanding with the opponent. Nonviolence does not seek to defeat the opponent. Nonviolence is directed against evil systems, forces, oppressive policies, unjust acts, but not against persons. Through reasoned compromise, both sides resolve the injustice with a plan of action. Each act of reconciliation is one step close to the ‘Beloved Community.’&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;beloved-community&quot;&gt;Beloved Community&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Beloved Community is a term coined by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Josiah_Royce&quot;&gt;Josiah Royce&lt;/a&gt;, founder of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://forusa.org/&quot;&gt;Fellowship of Reconciliation&lt;/a&gt;, of which King was a member. Dr. Kings vision of Beloved Community is a world of economic and social justice, where conflicts are resolved peacefully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Dr. King’s Beloved Community is a global vision, in which all people can share in the wealth of the earth. In the Beloved Community, poverty, hunger and homelessness will not be tolerated because international standards of human decency will not allow it. Racism and all forms of discrimination, bigotry and prejudice will be replaced by an all-inclusive spirit of sisterhood and brotherhood. In the Beloved Community, international disputes will be resolved by peaceful conflict-resolution and reconciliation of adversaries, instead of military power. Love and trust will triumph over fear and hatred. Peace with justice will prevail over war and military conflict. - &lt;a href=&quot;https://thekingcenter.org/about-tkc/the-king-philosophy/&quot;&gt;King Philosophy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;roots-of-violence&quot;&gt;Roots of Violence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gandhi and King have both achieved great works with nonviolent methods. They led movements that challenged the injustices in their worlds, and affected great change. They each held firm to a message of love, at the core of their frameworks for nonviolence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While their teaching and practices can be followed to great effect, if we wish to follow in their footsteps, it may serve us to first deal with the the source of violence in our lives, and understand how the ideology of violence proliferates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For that, we’ll explore two other important (but lesser-known than King or Gandhi) figures in nonviolence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;walter-wink-1935---2012&quot;&gt;Walter Wink (1935 - 2012)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/walter-wink.webp&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walter wink was an American biblical scholar, theologian, activist and advocate of nonviolent resistance. He had a way of uncovering potent truths in well-worn scriptures, and wrote &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/121850.Jesus_and_Nonviolence&quot;&gt;Jesus and Nonviolence: A Third Way&lt;/a&gt; describing &lt;a href=&quot;https://cpt.org/files/BN%20-%20Jesus%27%20Third%20Way.pdf&quot;&gt;Jesus’s message of nonviolence&lt;/a&gt;, as being far from passive resistance, but instead, as a radical and creative force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Jesus does not encourage Jews to walk a second mile in order to build up merit in heaven, or to be pious, or to kill the soldier with kindness. He is helping an oppressed people find a way to protest and neutralize an onerous practice despised throughout the empire. He is not giving a nonpolitical message of spiritual world transcendence. He is formulating a worldly spirituality in which the people at the bottom of society or under the thumb of imperial power learn to recover their humanity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wink’s explanation of Jesus’ nonviolence distinctly reminds me of the methods employed by Gandhi and King. I would highly recommend a reading of Wink along with the above mentioned &lt;a href=&quot;https://1lib.us/book/1309893/256eca&quot;&gt;Nonviolence: the history of a dangerous idea&lt;/a&gt;, by Mark Kurlansky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wink also is known for discovering the “Myth of Redemptive Violence”. He explains that this &lt;em&gt;myth of redemptive violence&lt;/em&gt; has a stronger grasp on the world than any other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The story that the rulers of domination societies told each other and their subordinates is what we today might call the Myth of Redemptive Violence. It enshrines the belief that violence saves, that war brings peace, that might makes right. It is one of the oldest continuously repeated stories in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www2.goshen.edu/~joannab/women/wink99.pdf&quot;&gt;Myth of Redemptive Violence&lt;/a&gt;, Walter Wink relates how he noticed this same pattern repeating in the structure of cartoons. There is a hero who suffers under the bad guy, and the hero has to vanquish the bad guy and restore order. They never reconcile or figure out creative ways to solve their problems, but forever repeat this same pattern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This pattern stretches back throughout recorded history, all the way back to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ancient.eu/article/225/enuma-elish---the-babylonian-epic-of-creation---fu/&quot;&gt;Enuma Elish&lt;/a&gt;, a Babylonian creation epic. Now that I’ve seen it, I see it everywhere. &lt;em&gt;Hidden in plain sight&lt;/em&gt; for thousands of years. I can’t help but think that Walter Wink is tremendously under-appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A domination system must have a domination myth, how­ ever, a story to explain how things got this way. For a story told often enough, and confirmed often enough in daily life, ceases to be a tale and is accepted as reality itself. And when that happens, people accept the story even if it is destroying their lives. – &lt;a href=&quot;https://1lib.us/book/2495538/aa9274&quot;&gt;The Powers That Be: Theology for a New Millennium&lt;/a&gt;, Walter Wink&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;marshall-b-rosenberg-1934---2015&quot;&gt;Marshall B. Rosenberg (1934 - 2015)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/marshall-rosenberg.webp&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If we change ourselves we can change the world, and changing ourselves begins with changing our language and methods of communication. -Arun Gandhi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marshall Rosenberg is an American psychologist who designed the process called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnvc.org/training/resource/book-chapter-1&quot;&gt;Nonviolent communication&lt;/a&gt;, and taught its practice and underlying philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growing up, Marshall Rosenberg experienced both tremendous violence, and great compassion. He studied psychology hoping to learn what made it so that some people come to enjoy violence and others give compassionately with joy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He saw that religions all agree that love and compassion are the way to live, but didn’t provide a process on how to go about how to live that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With his studies in psychology, learning from the people he knew who most enjoyed compassionate giving, and researching the best thought available on these subject, Marshall created a process, philosophy and practice called Nonviolent Communication (NVC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marshall often said that for over 10,000 years people have been living under domination structures where some claim to be superiors having the right to control others because they know what is best. The structures have educated us to use a language that disconnects us from our power, and look to authority on how to live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intwined with this language is a system of retributive justice that declares if you are judged as bad by the authorities then you deserve to suffer and be punished. If you are judged as good by authorities, then you deserve to be rewarded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Rosenberg believed that this system of thinking in a static way judging what people are, combined with the system of retributive justice, are at the heart of violence on our planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marshall Rosenberg often quoted Walter Wink, and his teaching of Nonviolent Communication elaborates how the Myth of Redemptive violence is born out in our thoughts and speech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;premise&quot;&gt;Premise&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonviolent communication is a language, philosophy and communication system designed with the intent that the needs of all participants are met.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That we give solely out of the joy that comes naturally from contributing to life, our own life and the lives of others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marshall tells us that others can’t make us feel anything, but its the way that we think that determines how we feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process of nonviolent communication provides us with the language, thinking, and practices that support us in connecting with ourselves and others in a way that promotes compassionate giving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NVC is practiced with the intention that whenever we give, its done solely out of the joy that comes naturally from contributing to life; our own life and the lives of others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The intention is that whatever we do is done willingly, not done out of guilt, shame, or fear of punishment, or trying to buy love, by submitting to what we think others expect us to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, that whatever we ask of others, we wish their cooperation only if it can be done with that same compassionate giving, never out of guilt, shame, or fear of punishment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inbal and Miki Kashtan highlight the following &lt;a href=&quot;https://baynvc.org/key-assumptions-and-intentions-of-nvc/&quot;&gt;Key Assumptions and Intentions of NVC&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All human beings share the same needs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All actions are attempts to meet needs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Feelings point to needs being met or unmet&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The most direct path to peace is through self-connection&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choice is internal&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All human beings have the capacity for compassion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Human beings enjoy giving&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Human beings meet needs through interdependent relationships&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our world offers abundant resources for meeting needs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Human beings change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll add a few ideas I think are close to the heart of NVC:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Never hear what people think about you, hear the need they are expressing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We often don’t recognize what need we’re trying to meet by an action.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conflicts often resolve when both parties recognize each-others needs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;process&quot;&gt;Process&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Avoid&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoid any language that sounds like criticism, blame, or insults.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoid presenting requests in a way where others hear demands.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anytime people hear criticism or demands, that makes it very difficult for people to enjoy contributing to one another’s well being.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;4-components-of-nonviolent-communication&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnvc.org/online-learning/nvc-instruction-guide/nvc-instruction-guide&quot;&gt;4 Components of Nonviolent Communication&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Observation&lt;/strong&gt;:  Observation without evaluation consists of noticing concrete things and actions around us. We learn to distinguish between judgment and what we sense in the present moment, and to simply observe what is there.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Feeling&lt;/strong&gt;:  When we notice things around us, we inevitably experience varying emotions and physical sensations in each particular moment. Here, distinguishing feelings from thoughts is an essential step to the NVC process.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Needs&lt;/strong&gt;:  All individuals have needs and values that sustain and enrich their lives. When those needs are met, we experience comfortable feelings, like happiness or peacefulness, and when they are not, we experience uncomfortable feelings, like frustration.  Understanding that we, as well as those around us, have these needs is perhaps the most important step in learning to practice NVC and to live empathically.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Request&lt;/strong&gt;:  To make clear and present requests is crucial to NVC’s transformative mission. When we learn to request concrete actions that can be carried out in the present moment, we begin to find ways to cooperatively and creatively ensure that everyone’s needs are met.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;distinguish-between&quot;&gt;Distinguish between&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Feelings vs. Thoughts&lt;/strong&gt; - We often use the words “I feel” followed by a description of what we think about a matter. Feelings are happy, sad, hurt, longing, angst, etc, rather than “I feel that is wrong”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Needs vs. Strategies&lt;/strong&gt; - Needs are universal and fundamental to life. We all have the same needs, such as food, shelter, acceptance and belonging. Strategies are how we seek to meet our needs. Our conflicts are always at the level of strategy, our conflicts are never at the level of our needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/power-love.webp&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mahatma Gandhi and Martin Luther King Jr are incredible examples of what is possible when nonviolent resistance is undertaken with a heart of love and compassion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difficulty is that the atmosphere of our times is not always conducive to nurturing that heart and spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walter Wink helps us to understand how we’ve learned to believe that violence saves, and paints a radical portrait of Jesus as using creative solutions to social injustice. Marshall Rosenberg expanded upon Wink’s message uncovering the root of violence in our language. He also furnished a system that helps to undo the ways of thinking that contribute to violence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve found that exploring the teachings of Walter Wink and Marshall Rosenberg have greatly improved my relationships and overall temperament, providing a means of working towards the purity of heart evidenced in the lives of heros like Martin Luther King Jr and Mahatma Gandhi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mettacenter.org/ppr/corporate-media-vs-nonviolence-podcast/&quot;&gt;Corporate Media vs Nonviolence – Podcast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://upsccivilservices.com/study_resources/download_report/33&quot;&gt;Gandhi - Socio-political Significance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://core.ac.uk/download/pdf/234717323.pdf&quot;&gt;Satyagraha: Gandhian Principles of Non-Violent Non-Cooperation&lt;/a&gt; William Stuart Nelson&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mkgandhi.org/africaneedsgandhi/gandhis_philosophy_of_nonviolence.htm&quot;&gt;Gandhi’s Philosophy of Nonviolence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://kpfa.org/episode/against-the-grain-november-11-2020/&quot;&gt;Kingian Nonviolence&lt;/a&gt; - KPFA, Against the Grain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thekingcenter.org/king-philosophy/&quot;&gt;The King Philosophy&lt;/a&gt; - King Center&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www2.goshen.edu/~joannab/women/wink99.pdf&quot;&gt;Myth of Redemptive Violence&lt;/a&gt;, Walter Wink&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SEL-ulRRMmk&quot;&gt;Walter Wink: Nonviolence for the Violent&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnvc.org/training/resource/book-chapter-1&quot;&gt;Nonviolent Communication: A Language of Life - Chapter 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnvc.org/sites/default/files/NVCInstructionGuide_Jiva_.pdf&quot;&gt;NVC Instruction Guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.satyagrahafoundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/02/gandhian-principles-for-everyday-living.pdf&quot;&gt;Nonviolent Communication: Gandhian Principles for Everyday Living&lt;/a&gt; by Miki Kashtan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;center&gt;Subscribe for Updates&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;form method=&quot;POST&quot; class=&quot;subscribe&quot; action=&quot;https://digitalskills.info/staticman/v2/entry/danforth-restorative/subscribe/master/subscribe&quot;&gt;
  &lt;input name=&quot;options[redirect]&quot; type=&quot;hidden&quot; value=&quot;https://danforth-restorative.com/thank-you/&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;options[slug]&quot; type=&quot;hidden&quot; value=&quot;restorative&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;input name=&quot;fields[name]&quot; type=&quot;text&quot; placeholder=&quot;Name&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;input name=&quot;fields[email]&quot; type=&quot;email&quot; placeholder=&quot;Email&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;&lt;textarea type=&quot;text&quot; rows=&quot;5&quot; cols=&quot;33&quot; placeholder=&quot;Your interest in this project.&quot; name=&quot;fields[message]&quot; tabindex=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;/textarea&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;&lt;button type=&quot;submit&quot;&gt;Subscribe&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/form&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;center&gt;Support this project on Patreon&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.patreon.com/bePatron?u=44125162&quot; data-patreon-widget-type=&quot;become-patron-button&quot;&gt;Become a Patron!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://c6.patreon.com/becomePatronButton.bundle.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt;</content><author><name>David Danforth</name></author><category term="Nonviolence" /><summary type="html">Gandhi and King offer powerful examples of what is possible with a commitment to nonviolent resistance, fueled by love. Their nonviolent practices have been followed to great effect, but their examples of love, in the face of oppression are difficult to follow. That could have something to do with that theologian Walter Wink called the Myth of Redemptive Violence, a pattern that's been repeated in nearly every story ever told.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://danforth-restorative.com/assets/images/Rise-of-Nonviolence.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://danforth-restorative.com/assets/images/Rise-of-Nonviolence.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Danforth Restorative and DigitalSkills.Info</title><link href="https://danforth-restorative.com/2020/10/07/digitalskills-restorative.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Danforth Restorative and DigitalSkills.Info" /><published>2020-10-07T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-01-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://danforth-restorative.com/2020/10/07/digitalskills-restorative</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://danforth-restorative.com/2020/10/07/digitalskills-restorative.html">&lt;p&gt;This is my personal blog, but it is also a place to share knowledge related to personal growth and social change. This post describes that relationship, and its connection to &lt;a href=&quot;https://digitalskills.info&quot;&gt;digitalskills.info&lt;/a&gt; where I share information related to developing digital skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-personal-blog&quot;&gt;A Personal Blog&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One purpose of this blog is to provide a space to reflect upon my addictions recovery, and share resources I’ve found most valuable for rebuilding my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will try to be vulnerable, and open up about some of my struggles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I’ve learned during this process is that focusing too much on my problems can get in the way of solving them. I’ve found it more productive to focus on developing strengths than to focus on my problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its easy to get lost in self-judgement, the pain of remembrance, and dwelling on my failings. I’ve used that pain as a powerful incentive, devoting my energy to study, and the hard work of creating a life worth living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is a continual practice, working towards positive for myself and others – a slow incremental process that, little by little, has restored vibrancy to life – restructuring my thoughts, habits, hobbies and means of living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;danforth-restorative&quot;&gt;Danforth Restorative&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog is also a place to share valuable resources that have been valuable in my healing process. Part of that has been getting beyond my personal struggles, and joining in on the rallying cry around social issues I’ve stayed willfully ignorant about for too long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to acknowledge the systemic problems of sexism and racism, and make the information surrounding them easier to navigate. This is for my own education, to make them more approachable for others, on the web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important to be aware of our personal and societal problems, but also to get practical, seeking creative ways to solve them. For me, that involves creative use of digital tools, and some techniques for sharing information that I’ve found to be effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;digitalskillsinfo&quot;&gt;DigitalSkills.Info&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;digital-skills-a-force-multiplier&quot;&gt;Digital Skills A Force Multiplier&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to my personal studies, I’ve spent these years of recovery immersed in the challenge of developing marketable digital skills. I think for the first couple years, my research was a kind of replacement addiction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there can be some challenging repercussions for obsessive studying, overall it’s much better than drinking!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drawing my focus on the multitude of challenges, technical and otherwise, of building a career online, I was able to find some relief from the initial agony of sobriety and facing my internal processes loud and clear, after years of dulling my senses in drink and drug.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That process has been very empowering, I got a taste for the impact one person can make on the web, simply making useful information more accessible. I’ve also gotten a taste for the powerful tools available on the web, and how they can multiply the impact that one person can create.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;digital-skills-personal-growth-social-struggles-and-transformative-potential&quot;&gt;Digital skills, personal growth, social struggles, and transformative potential&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The focus of DigitalSkills.Info is to help make digital skills more accessible. On one hand, they are increasingly required to be employable. On the other hand, these skills can prove invaluable for creating the social impact we want to see in the world.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>David Danforth</name></author><category term="Danforth Restorative" /><summary type="html">This is my personal blog, but it is also a place to share knowledge related to personal growth and social change. This post describes that relationship, and its connection to digitalskills.info where I share information related to developing digital skills.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://danforth-restorative.com/assets/images/Danforth-Restorative-og_MAKY_OREL.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://danforth-restorative.com/assets/images/Danforth-Restorative-og_MAKY_OREL.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Introduction to Nonviolent Communication</title><link href="https://danforth-restorative.com/2020/07/22/nonviolent-communication.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introduction to Nonviolent Communication" /><published>2020-07-22T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-07-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://danforth-restorative.com/2020/07/22/nonviolent-communication</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://danforth-restorative.com/2020/07/22/nonviolent-communication.html">&lt;p&gt;Nonviolent communication is a value system designed to promote peace on the planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It includes a philosophy and communication framework that lead to compassionate giving and meeting the needs of all participants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Nonviolent-Communication_Language-of-Life.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first encountered this message in a youtube video from an April 2000 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=l7TONauJGfc&quot;&gt;introductory workshop hosted by Marshall Rosenberg&lt;/a&gt;. In this video, Marshall shares stories of using this technique for negotiation in longstanding tribal conflicts, racial violence, marital disputes and healing emotional wounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonviolent communication provides clarity around how we think about our emotions and fundamental human needs, laying the groundwork for empathic connection with the people in our lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- excerpt --&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/l7TONauJGfc&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marshall_Rosenberg&quot;&gt;Marshall Rosenberg&lt;/a&gt; developed this system after having grown up experiencing, both, extreme violence and compassion under difficult conditions. He went on to study psychology with the intention to discover what conditions contribute to violence on the planet and what helps us connect us with our compassionate nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earning a Ph.D. in clinical psychology from the University of Wisconsin–Madison, Dr. Rosenberg found that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2019/07/190708131152.htm&quot;&gt;psychiatric diagnoses have no scientific basis&lt;/a&gt;, and that looking at violence as a mental illness ignored the societal structures that promote this behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He found that religions of the world agree we’re meant to live compassionately, but don’t necessarily explain how to do that. He then studied the differences between the people, he knew, who were the most compassionate, and those who seemed to enjoy criticizing, blaming, and attacking others. He used this research along with his education in psychology to develop this process of called nonviolent communication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While developing NVC, he found the process to be much more effective as a healing tool, in his practice of clinical psychology, than how he was taught to do psychotherapy in university.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;premise&quot;&gt;Premise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonviolent communication requires a radical transformation of our habits in communication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Rosenberg suggests that people have been &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.opendemocracy.net/en/transformation/transforming-powers-continuing-relevance-of-walter-wink/&quot;&gt;living under domination structures&lt;/a&gt; for most of recorded history, where some people claim to be superior, having the right to control others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People living under those structures have been taught a system of retributive justice, where if you are judged as good by authorities then you deserve to be rewarded, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www2.goshen.edu/~joannab/women/wink99.pdf&quot;&gt;if you are judged as bad by the authorities, you deserve to suffer&lt;/a&gt;. Additionally, we’ve learned to use a type of &lt;em&gt;language that describes what people are&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;strong&gt;good&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;bad&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;right&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;wrong&lt;/strong&gt;; rather than how their actions impact our lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Rosenberg taught that whenever we’re feeling anger, depression, guilt, or shame, we’re thinking in a way that contributes to violence, a way of thinking designed to make us obedient to authority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OJ Harvey took samples of literature from around the world to discover how often language was used judging people’s actions in this way, and then correlated that with measures of violence towards oneself and others, finding a high &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/stream/conceptualsystem00harv/conceptualsystem00harv_djvu.txt&quot;&gt;correlation between the language of moralistic judgement and violence&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast, Nonviolent communication focuses our attention on whether actions peoples actions are fulfilling our needs or not. Our own actions, and the actions of others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of judging what people are, we make clear observations of whether their actions are fulfilling our needs. If our needs are not met, then we follow up our observation with a clear request of what would meet those needs. If our needs are met by their actions, we clearly communicate an appreciation of how our lives have been enriched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;components&quot;&gt;Components&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The language of nonviolent communication consists of &lt;strong&gt;Feelings&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Needs&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Observations&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Requests&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;feelings&quot;&gt;Feelings&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process of nonviolent communication begins with our feelings, and requires that we learn to identify and name our emotions. To help with that there are some lists of different type of feeling words.  To say ‘I feel good’, or ‘I feel bad’, isn’t very descriptive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we do feel good, there are likely a number of other words that would more adequately convey what’s alive in us. Just as when we aren’t feeling well, there are more descriptive words that can more accurately convey our emotional state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;our-feelings-when-needs-are-met&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nycnvc.org/feelings/&quot;&gt;Our Feelings When Needs are Met&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AFFECTIONATE&lt;/strong&gt;: compassionate, fond, loving, 
tender, warm&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ENGAGED&lt;/strong&gt;: absorbed, curious, engrossed, enthralled, entranced, fascinated, interested, intrigued, involved, open, spellbound, stimulated&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EXCITED&lt;/strong&gt;: amazed, ardent, aroused, energetic, enlivened, enthusiastic, exuberant, invigorated, lively, passionate, surprised, vibrant&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EXHILARATED&lt;/strong&gt;: enthralled, radiant, electrified, overjoyed, thrilled&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GRATEFUL&lt;/strong&gt;: appreciative, moved, thankful, touched&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HAPPY&lt;/strong&gt;: amused, blissful, cheerful, ecstatic, elated, giddy, glad, jolly, joyful, jubilant, merry, overjoyed, pleased, rapturous, tickled&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HOPEFUL&lt;/strong&gt;: confident, expectant, jazzed, sanguine, up, upbeat&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;INSPIRED&lt;/strong&gt;: amazed, eager, enthused, moved, psyched, stimulated, stirred, wonder&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PEACEFUL&lt;/strong&gt;: calm, comfortable, centered, equanimity, fulfilled, mellow, open, quiet, relaxed, relieved, satisfied, serene, tranquil&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;REFRESHED&lt;/strong&gt;: recharged, rejuvenated, renewed, restored, revived&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;feelings-associated-with-unmet-needs&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nycnvc.org/feelings/&quot;&gt;Feelings Associated with Unmet Needs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ANGER&lt;/strong&gt;: aggravated, angry, animosity, annoyed, contempt, disgruntled, enraged, furious, hate , hostile, incensed, irate, irritated, irked, livid, nettled, outraged, peeved, resentful&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AVERSION&lt;/strong&gt;: abhorrence, appalled, bothered displeased, disgust, dislike, enmity, horrified, loathing, repulsion, revulsion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CONFUSION&lt;/strong&gt;: ambivalent, baffled bewildered, conflicted, dazed, discombobulated, disoriented, mixed, mystified, perplexed, puzzled, torn&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DISCONNECTION&lt;/strong&gt;: apathetic, bored, closed, 
detached, distant, indifferent, listless, numb, withdrawn&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DISQUIET&lt;/strong&gt;: agitated, alarmed, concerned, distraught, disconcerted, dismayed, disturbed, frustrated, perturbed, rattled, restless, shocked, startled, surprised, troubled, turbulent, turmoil, uncomfortable, uneasy, unnerved, unsettled, upset&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EMBARRASSMENT&lt;/strong&gt;: ashamed, chagrined, discomfited, flustered, mortified, self-conscious&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FATIGUE&lt;/strong&gt;: beat, burnt out, depleted, exhausted, listless, pooped, sleepy, tired, weary, wiped out, worn out&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FEAR&lt;/strong&gt;: afraid, anxious, apprehensive, dread, fearful, foreboding, frightened, guarded,  insecure, leery, mistrustful, panicked, petrified, scared, shaky, terrified,  trepidation, wary, worried&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PAIN&lt;/strong&gt;: aching, agony, anguished, devastated, grief, heartbroken, hungry, hurting, lonely, miserable, regretful, remorseful&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SADNESS&lt;/strong&gt;: depressed, dejected, despairing, despondent, disappointed, discouraged, disheartened, forlorn, gloomy, heavy hearted,  hopeless, melancholy, miserable, unhappy, wistful&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TENSION&lt;/strong&gt;: anxious, closed, distressed, 
edgy, fidgety, frazzled, frustrated, jittery,nervous, overwhelmed, restless, stressed out&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;YEARNING&lt;/strong&gt;: longing, nostalgic, pining&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“People are disturbed not by things, but by the view they take of them.” —Epictetus&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important premise underlying nonviolent communication is that it’s our thinking that causes our emotions, not external events. Other people’s words or behavior may very well be the stimulus for our feelings, but they are never the cause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;needs&quot;&gt;Needs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In nonviolent communication, part of understanding our feelings is identifying which needs of ours are related to those feelings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Rosenberg developed a list of what he determined to be &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nycnvc.org/feelings/&quot;&gt;funadmental human needs&lt;/a&gt;, based on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.daghammarskjold.se/wp-content/uploads/1989/05/89_1.pdf&quot;&gt;the work of Max-Neef&lt;/a&gt;, a Chilean economist who determined that the best way to measure an economy based on whether it’s meeting the needs of its people or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;needs-inventory&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnvc.org/training/resource/needs-inventory&quot;&gt;Needs Inventory&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;(c) 2005 by Center for Nonviolent Communication&lt;br /&gt;
Website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnvc.org&quot;&gt;www.cnvc.org&lt;/a&gt; Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:cnvc@cnvc.org&quot;&gt;cnvc@cnvc.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Phone: +1.505-244-4041&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CONNECTION&lt;/strong&gt;: acceptance, affection, appreciation, belonging, cooperation, communication, closeness, community, companionship, compassion, consideration, consistency, empathy, inclusion, intimacy, love, mutuality, nurturing, respect/self-respect, safety, security, stability, support, to know and be known, to see and be seen, to understand and be understood, trust, warmth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PHYSICAL WELL-BEING&lt;/strong&gt;: air, food, movement/exercise, rest/sleep, sexual expression, safety, shelter, touch, water&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HONESTY&lt;/strong&gt;: authenticity, integrity, presence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PLAY&lt;/strong&gt;: joy, humor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PEACE&lt;/strong&gt;: beauty, communion, ease, equality, harmony, inspiration, order&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AUTONOMY&lt;/strong&gt;: choice, freedom, independence, space, spontaneity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MEANING&lt;/strong&gt;: awareness, celebration of life, challenge, clarity, competence, consciousness, contribution, creativity, discovery, efficacy, effectiveness, growth, hope, learning, mourning, participation, purpose, self-expression, stimulation, to matter, understanding&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;needs-vs-strategies&quot;&gt;Needs vs Strategies&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A premise of NVC is that all actions are attempts to meet human needs, and that our conflicts are never at the level of those needs, but in the strategies we employ attempting to meet those needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking for the un-met need helps us to transcend the strategy level, where we can easily get caught in conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;observations&quot;&gt;Observations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The ability to observe without evaluating is the highest form of intelligence.” - Jiddu Krishnamurti&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Begin with a clear observation of what behavior has stimulating our emotions, avoiding language that sounds like criticism or blame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This part might sound simple, but we’re accustomed to making evaluations of what type of person they are, because of their actions, rather than how those actions affected our needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Observations are contrasted with diagnoses. An observation connected with a need might sound like, “I have a need for tranquility when its time for bed, and when you didn’t come home on time angry and afraid”. The diagnosis could sound like “you don’t care about me, you only ever think of yourself”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of those statements could be a response to the same situation, but in nonviolent communication we avoid diagnosing what we think people are. We create clear observations of a behavior and which needs of ours were, or were not, met by that behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;requests&quot;&gt;Requests&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If our needs are not met in a situation, it’s important to be clear what would meet our needs in this moment, avoiding vague language, or only stating what you don’t want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We might like for others to anticipate our needs before we even are aware of them, but often we’re not very clear ourselves about exactly what will meet our needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;requests-vs-demands&quot;&gt;Requests vs Demands&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Avoid presenting requests in a way that sound like a demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever we get people to do things from fear of punishment, shame or guilt, we are experienced as a source of violence, who will make the suffer if they don’t comply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To illustrate the danger of a language that denies choice, Rosenberg provides the example of Nazi war criminal Adolph Eichmann.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At his war trial, asked if it was difficult to send thousands to their deaths, Eichmann responded that their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Sk9-3bMAGBw&quot;&gt;bureaucratic language&lt;/a&gt; made it easy. If someone asked why they did it, they would say ‘I had no choice’, ‘superiors orders’, ‘it’s the law’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of this concern, nonviolent communication emphasizes that we avoid any language that implies we have no choice, and suggests that the use of words like ‘have to’, ‘ought’, ‘must’ results in people who don’t feel responsible for their actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonviolent communication has a handful of moving parts, and involves learning a new way to think about ourselves and our relationships. While it’s not an overly complex system, it does express some profound truths that I’m not sure I’m able to properly convey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most impactful, to me, is the concept of retributive justice. I’ve begun to see how deeply ingrained it is, in my own consciousness, and the world around me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel like there’s a lot of ground for me to cover still, in nonviolent communication. I intend to spend a lot more time working on this, what I believe to be the most valuable teaching available for promoting peace on the plant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;further-study&quot;&gt;Further Study&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some links where you can find more information in Articles, Books, Video, Podcasts, and Research Studies&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnvc.org/&quot;&gt;Center for Nonviolent Communication&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnvc.org/training/resource/book-chapter-1&quot;&gt;Nonviolent Communication: A Language of Life&lt;/a&gt; - Chapter 1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nonviolentcommunication.com/learn-nonviolent-communication/&quot;&gt;PuddleDancer Press&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://puddledancer.bookstore.ipgbook.com/&quot;&gt;NVC Bookstore&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nonviolentcommunication.com/learn-nonviolent-communication/research-on-nvc/&quot;&gt;Research&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=l7TONauJGfc&quot;&gt;The Basics of Nonviolent Communication, with Marshall B. Rosenberg, PhD&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLPNVcESwoWu4lI9C3bhkYIWB8-dphbzJ3&quot;&gt;NVC Training Sessions 1-9 Marshall Rosenberg Nonviolent Communication&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://workcollaboratively.com/podcast/&quot;&gt;Connecting Across Differences&lt;/a&gt; - a podcast by Dian Killian, Ph.D. of Work Collaboratively about having greater empathy for yourself and others, and how to hear others more deeply and make sure that you’ve been heard.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.artofnvc.com/podcast-1&quot;&gt;The Art of NVC&lt;/a&gt; - Podcast dedicated to sharing, learning, and discovering the fundamentals of Nonviolent Communication based on what I have learned from Marshall Rosenberg’s classic book “Nonviolent Communication” and many of his videos.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>David Danforth</name></author><category term="Nonviolence" /><summary type="html">Instead of judging what people are, we make clear observations of whether their actions are fulfilling our needs. If our needs are not met, then we follow up our observation with a clear request of what would meet those needs. If our needs are met by their actions, we clearly communicate an appreciation of how our lives have been enriched.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://danforth-restorative.com/assets/images/Nonviolent-Communication.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://danforth-restorative.com/assets/images/Nonviolent-Communication.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Opening up after a few years of isolation, since I stopped drinking</title><link href="https://danforth-restorative.com/2020/07/20/introduction.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Opening up after a few years of isolation, since I stopped drinking" /><published>2020-07-20T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-07-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://danforth-restorative.com/2020/07/20/introduction</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://danforth-restorative.com/2020/07/20/introduction.html">&lt;p&gt;I quit drinking and drugs almost three years ago, although I’ve only been approaching something resembling sobriety since the beginning of this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I quit drinking, I’d been on a downward spiral for quite some time. My behavior and mindset deteriorated to a shameful state. I was stuck in a cycle of addiction that I didn’t know how to escape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I drank, I didn’t have to be concerned with anything of import, I’d regulate my emotions with a 6 pack. I knew I had to find a different way, but that was easier said than done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gratefully, I had some help coming to the stark realization of exactly how far I’d fallen, and a family who cares to support the long road of recovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- excerpt --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/david.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I grew up with a lot of pain that I attributed to the world around me. While I had some just grievances, much of my angst was misguided. It’s taken far too too long, for me to realize that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead I bitterly rejected what I saw as adversarial social convention meant to control. I inherently distrusted all social structures, which was a direct impediment to becoming a part of anything larger than myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I set out, in 2007, as a seeker of truth. I had the idea that the world was broken. That corruption and lies were embedded into every sphere of life, that the system was set up against the many for the benefit of the few. While that may be true, my reaction to those perceived injustices increased my own suffering and that of others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I shed the external trappings of domination, I sought fulfillment in drugs, alcohol, sex, self-serving pursuits and fleeting experiences. I was full of bitterness, on a self-indulgent trip simply trying to escape, doing nothing to improve my situation or the world around me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the intervening years, plenty of others have worked tirelessly, to make the world a better place, and improved many of the issues I care about.. while I was falling behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a lot of remorse, and have suffered a great deal of anguish, about some of my actions, and state of being, over the years I spent on the road. I was judgemental, self-righteous, had an unhealthy attitude towards women, made increasingly poor decisions, and grew to cherish my addictions over reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m here to try and speak to all of that, make clear where my current state of mind and intentions are at, and begin working to improve situations that I’ve negatively impacted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nonviolent-communication&quot;&gt;Nonviolent Communication&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A major turning point in my recovery has been finding &lt;a href=&quot;https://baynvc.org/basics-of-nonviolent-communication/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nonviolent Communication&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (NVC). I started listening to workshops given by Marshall Rosenberg, at the recommendation of my counselor. NVC is now the cornerstone to my recovery, easily the most valuable teaching I’ve ever encountered, and the main reason I’m here and able to write this message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d heard about Nonviolent Communication years ago, once upon a time I thought I knew generally what it was, and even practiced it to a limited extent. I can see now that I had no inkling of its depth or potency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Nonviolent communication (NVC) consists of a value system that challenges ways of thinking that create violence on this planet. 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnvc.org/training/resource/book-chapter-1&quot;&gt;Nonviolent Communication: A Language of Life&lt;/a&gt; - Marshall Rosenberg&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of nonviolent communication is to communicate in such a way where the needs of all participants are met, so that co-operation is come to willingly, never out of guilt, shame, or from trying to buy approval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even being new to the subject, learning about the process and it’s underlying philosophy, my relationship with family rapidly improved, and I was able to move past a great deal of anger, by recognizing where it’s misplaced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The message of Nonviolent Communication has helped to begin repairing old wounds, and show me a path towards life enriching human relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;trying-to-find-a-path-forward&quot;&gt;Trying to find a path forward&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important for me to not only find healing, but make whatever positive impact in the lives of others that I’m able, and perhaps repair some of the damage I perpetuated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past year, I’ve delved into Cognitive Behavioral Therapy (CBT), emotional literacy, mindfulness, restorative practices, the mechanics behind addiction, and important messages that are gaining traction lately, including that Black Lives Matter and the #metoo movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not able to devote all of my time to these pursuits, but my energy has been shifting in that direction, since around the new year. I have been saving up a lot of bookmarks, so I’d like to begin sharing regularly on &lt;em&gt;all of the above&lt;/em&gt; and see where that goes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>David Danforth</name></author><category term="Danforth Restorative" /><summary type="html">I quit drinking and drugs almost three years ago, although I've only been approaching something resembling sobriety since the beginning of this year.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://danforth-restorative.com/assets/images/Danforth-Restorative-og_MAKY_OREL.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://danforth-restorative.com/assets/images/Danforth-Restorative-og_MAKY_OREL.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>